okay ready okay sit like a rock sit like
a rock rocks don't open books and things
like that
everybody has to die normally if they
don't practice well enough everybody has
to die and during the death process
there's a special opportunity to see
emptiness directly so the purpose of
this meditation is to practice what it
feels like to die until you get to the
point in death when you have a window of
opportunity to see emptiness if you know
what you're doing if you don't it'll
just pass and you will be reborn
someplace so here we go
come watch your body
sit up straight pull in your stomach
slightly and keep it there just a slight
pressure
relax your eyelids small Mona Lisa smile
[Music]
fingers are relaxed shoulders are
relaxed and pulled back shoulder blades
together in the back
brighten up your forehead relax it
release it open it and don't punch it up
when we start focusing to keep it light
and your eye mates are super relaxed if
you feel sleepy you can crack your
eyelids open but don't look
relax the corners of your mouth and then
slowly come to your breaths like getting
in the saddle of a horse this is your
getting into the saddle of your
meditation come to your breath and start
focusing on the long exhales so the
inhales will take care of themselves or
else you're dead already
and they'll slowly naturally comfortably
start to follow with accounting each
exhale is one next exhale is two and see
if you can stay with your breath sliding
in and out without thinking about
something else just be here you're stuck
here for a week you can't go anywhere no
use to worry about your job or your
family or the world or what did Trump do
this morning just forget it for a week
and come to your breath that's all
you're supposed to do
let me imagine where it is you might be
dying in this life if you died this
month next month where might you be I
think my child will probably be on my
bed at home you know I would die it in
my home so think about that bed and
imagine you are lying in it something
happened you got hurt in a car accident
or something happen in your you are in
your last few minutes in this world
you're on the bed and you will not get
off of the bed a lot
you're looking up and close friends
close family are with you some can be
holding your hands I'm holding your feet
they might be crying they don't want you
to leave and you don't want to leave but
and death will take you
your fingers are getting a little cold
hard to move them your feet shall call
very hard to breathe not easy to get air
through your nose or to your mouth
families talking softly but it's getting
difficult to hear what they're saying
you're called it almost all the way up
your legs and arms
can't hear the family anymore can't move
your arms or legs anymore your mouth
closes and your nose your nostrils shut
inside and you stop breathing can't
breathe and your mind your consciousness
starts to withdraw from the world your
eyes closed for the last time you can't
open them you would like to about your
kids
and the thoughts withdraw into the
middle of your mind and you're alone and
they start and it's Tyler
and suddenly it's as if you're walking I
like to picture myself close to those
big mountains in Diamond Mountain behind
the retreat valley I'm walking down the
bottom part going downhill and then
suddenly the pieces of rock huge pieces
of rock the size of your retreat cottage
the size of cars are are breaking off
the mountain rolling down the mountain
you can see if you look at that mountain
sometime you can see where pieces of
rock like that have come down you can
see the path they followed and then
crushing everything in their path and
you're running you start to run ahead of
this huge boulders were rolling down the
hill behind you the noise is terrible
like a many car accidents at the same
time and you're running the earth
element is collapsing inside of you then
suddenly behind the mountain comes a
huge tsunami wave like the one that took
your pen and it's moving very fast a
huge unbelievable unimaginable almost
blocks out the skies and you're hopeless
in front of it and you're running as
fast as you can but the wave catches you
and throws you into the water you're
finding
just to get some more bad you are
surrounded by huge ways you're in the
water
struggling being dragged down and I I
personally when I do this meditation I
think of Dyna Mountain I'm being pushed
by the waves down into the valley here
past this temple and I'm just fighting
to try to get some breath some air and I
just to make the meditation easier the
visualization easier for me I imagine it
carries me out 1012 miles through belief
and to the other side is just flat
desert then the water element has
dissolved and you're just laying
suddenly the water leaves you in the
desert and the water drains away and you
are crawling across the desert and the
Sun comes up very very large filling
most of the sky like no normal Sun and
the fire element in your bodies is
dissolving and it feels terrible heat it
feels like being inside of a fire and
you're crawling I imagine crawling away
from Bowie across the desert fire all
around me
then the fire starts to wear out and
then this huge wind storm comes across
the desert like a singapore hurricane
tearing across the desert and it's
tearing at your body things are flying
past you trees rocks dust the wind is
tearing at your body this is the wind
element is dissolving and then suddenly
that starts to dissipate and you're I
imagine standing walking slowly ahead no
place to go just alone in a empty
landscape and I'm walking ahead and far
away I can see a mirage and these are
the subtle elements of your body are
breaking down and you see way in the
distance you see light it looks like an
egg shimmering but it's just a mirage
and you walk towards it and you get
closer and closer and you actually walk
through the Mirage and on the other side
in the other land it's all just like fog
or smoke you are walking through dense
smoke or fog there's nothing you can see
in front of you if you put your hand on
in front of you you can't see it
everything is thick fog smoke
you're walking still hopelessly driven
to a head to the smoke and then you
start to see sparks in the smoke they
say like fireflies or sparks from some
machines and you can see sparks here and
there in the air in front of you and
around you these are parts of your
consciousness are breaking down as you
go deeper into death then ahead of you
you can see a very steady fire same like
a candle flames so the world is getting
smaller your world is shrinking it feels
like you're going through a tunnel which
gets more and more narrow and at the end
of the tunnel in the dark you can see a
single candle flame in mobile it's
burning but it's not moving there's no
win just to study unmoving candle flame
when you're walking towards the slave
then you actually walk through the flame
because you're only a small note your
world is very small and on the other
side of the flame it's just like
everything around you total blood and
still you're walking and then somehow
the blood gets deeper deeper blood than
the one before so try to imagine deeper
blood all around you like ink and then
suddenly you're enter deeper deeper
black total darkness you can't see your
feet you can't see your arms you can
just seek darkness total complete
darkness
it's still walking then slowly in the
horizon and for me I like to imagine the
east side of the retreat Valley those of
you who did a three-year retreat when
the Sun daybreak comes before sunrise
this daybreak before the Sun breaks the
horizon then to the east there's this
white color of the sky before the yellow
comes there's a white and that white in
front of you behind the horizon it
begins to spread all around you and you
are surrounded by white light
and you're still walking
and then a red light like a sunset
starts to replace the white light and
you are walking through a world of red
light and then slowly the red light
dissolves and you come to another
darkness black deeper black very deeply
then suddenly things change and it feels
like you're walking inside of crystal
like there's a crystalline feeling to
the to the world around you you are
surrounded in a kind of crystal or the
the air is crystal like diamond as if
you're walking to divert but you can
breathe and you can walk but the world
around you is like diamond and in this
point of death your central channels
broken open all the chocolates have
broken open and the bran is flowing
freely with no obstacle at this point
you your physical body releases peepee
poo-poo but you're you're not aware of
it because you are deep deep deep inside
and at this point you can grab this
small few minutes of opportunity to
think about emptiness you can think
about how nothing you see is not coming
from you everything you see around you
everything you're experiencing every
thought every feeling in this moment is
coming from seeds in your mind and
there's nothing around there which is
coming from the outside it's all coming
from inside you so cancel the idea that
anything's happening to you it's all
happening from you and hope that and
we'll stay here for a few minutes try to
stay in the feeling that everything you
thought was there coming from its own
side never was in bad tempting
then you can start to come out of that
emptiness I like to come out standing on
the sky as a Buddha and I'm suddenly
come outta there not not to rebirth but
I come into a Buddha and I'm standing
above a planet looking down maybe it's a
night time and it looks beautiful with
all the lights of the cities this is the
world that I have to take care of and be
there
serve them guard them I like to stand
there with my teacher who in in the
diamond right teachings Vajrayana it's
my partner in the mirror
sort of like mommy and daddy looking at
a world thinking we're going to take
care of it
then follow your brats for three breaths
three deep access to get ready to come
out just relax don't get it
you know too excited about coming up
then slowly open your eyes on the last
inhale take a stretch it's good when you
meditate to take stretches that's what
yoga was originally for right